

COMPUTER SCIENCE P.H.D CANDIDATE INTERESTED IN THE APPLICATION OF NLP METHODS IN COMPUTATIONAL SOCIAL SCIENCE

Unter Sachsenhausen 6-8, Cologne 50667, Germany

🛮 +49(221)47694-253 | 🖪 Indira.Sen@gesis,org | 🎢 https://indiiigo.github.io/ | 🖸 Indiiigo | 💆 @indiiigosky | Google Scholar

Research Interests_

I'm interested in improving the measurement of political and prejudicial attitudes and behaviours from digital trace data using mixed-methods and natural language processing. My research aims to illuminate and characterize the potentials, pitfalls, and consequences of understanding such attitudes from unobtrusive digital traces.

Education _____

GESIS - Leibnitz Institute for Social Sciences

Cologne, Germany

P.H.D IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

2018 - Present

ADVISOR: PROF. CLAUDIA WAGNER

Indraprastha Institute of Information Technology (IIIT-D)

New Delhi, India

M.S IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

2015 - 2017

ADVISOR: PROF. PONNURANGAM KUMARAGURU (PK)

GPA: 8.67/10

Vellore Institute of Technology (VIT)

Vellore, India

B.S IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

2010 - 2014

GPA: 9.1/10

Honors & Awards __

2021	Summer Intern Award for Outstanding Innovation, Nokia Bell Labs	Cambridge, UK / virtual
2021	Best Reviewer Award, ICWSM	virtual
2020	Travel Grant for attending EMNLP,	virtual
2020	Selected for SAGE Text-Mining Fellowship, SAGE, Ocean	London, UK (virtual)
2020	Selected as Facilitator for the Alan Turing Institute Data Study Group, 2 week hackathon where we worked with an Industry partner (CatsAI) to deploy explainable AI predictions	virtual
2020	Accepted to MLSS 2020, One of the 160 participants out 1100 application accepted to participate in the highly competitive machine learning summer school	virtual
2020	Travel Grant, For attending FAT* 2020	Barcelona, Spain
2019	Travel Grant, For attending Summer Institute in Computational Social Science (SICCS), Germany	Bamberg, Germany
2017	TA Excellence Award, Foundations of Computer Security	IIIT-Delhi, India
2017	Accepted to Summer@EPFL, One of 60 interns selected out of 2000 applications	EPFL, Switzerland
2015- 2016	Dean's Merit List, For Academic Performance	IIIT-Delhi, India
2015	GATE Scholarship, Scholarship for Master's Studies	
2011- 2014	Merit Scholarship, For Outstanding Academic Achievement	VIT, Vellore

Publications _____

Journal Articles

A Total Error Framework for Digital Traces of Human Behavior on Online Platforms

2021

INDIRA SEN, FABIAN FLOECK, KATRIN WELLER, BERND WEISS, AND CLAUDIA WAGNER. PUBLIC OPINION QUARTERLY

OCTOBER 28, 2021 INDIRA SEN · CV 1

Conference Articles

Constructs?	2021
INDIRA SEN, MATTIA SAMORY, FABIAN FLOECK, CLAUDIA WAGNER AND ISABELLE AUGENSTEIN.	
Conference on Empirical Methods on Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)	
"Call me sexist, but": Revisiting Sexism Detection Using Psychological Scales and Adversarial Samples	2021
MATTIA SAMORY, INDIRA SEN , JULIAN KOHNE, FABIAN FLOECK, AND CLAUDIA WAGNER. ACCEPTED AT INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON WEB AND SOCIAL MEDIA (ICWSM) 2021	
On the Reliability and Validity of Detecting Approval of Political Actors in Tweets Indira Sen, Fabian Floeck, and Claudia Wagner.	2020
CONFERENCE ON EMPIRICAL METHODS ON NATURAL LANGUAGE PROCESSING (EMNLP)	
Empowering First Responders through Automated Multimodal Content Moderation	2018
Divam Gupta, Indira Sen , Niharika Sachdeva, Ponnurangam Kumaraguru, Arun Balaji Buduru. EEE International Conference on Cognitive Computing	Best Paper Award
Worth its Weight in Likes: Towards Detecting Fake Likes on Instagram	2018
Indira Sen, Anupama Aggarwal, Shiven Mian, Siddharth Singh, Ponnurangam Kumaraguru, Anwitaman Datta. WebSci 2018, short paper	
Workshop Articles	
What Human Rationales Tell us about Machine Explanations	2021
Indira Sen, Mattia Samory, Fabian Floeck, Claudia Wagner HCI+NLP Workshop, In conjunction with EACL	
Measuring Public Opinion Online: Potentials and Pitfalls	2020
Indira Sen, Fabian Floeck, Claudia Wagner	Poster
Nomen in Machine Learning (WiML), In conjunction with Neurips	
A Twitter Corpus for Hindi-English Code Mixed POS Tagging	2018
Kushagra Singh, Indira Sen , Ponnurangam Kumaraguru. Workshop on Natural Language Processing for Social Media (SocialNLP), In conjunction with ACL	Data Paper
Language Identification and Named Entity Recognition in Hinglish Code Mixed Tweets Kushagra Singh, Indira Sen, Ponnurangam Kumaraguru. ACL Student Research Workshop	2018
Experience	
Nokia Bell Labs	Cambridge, UK (virtual)
NTERN AT SOCIAL DYNAMICS GROUP. ADVISORS: DR. DANIELE QUERCIA	Jun 2021 - Aug 2021
Understanding and Characterizing the sustainability efforts of companies from employee reviews. Developed a mixed-method techniques for detecting employees' views on their employer's sustainability efforts using a deep-learning framework (sBERT)	
Results from the internship are currently in preparation for publication.	
SAGE Ocean	London, UK (virtual)
SAGE OCEAN FELLOW. ADVISORS: DR. DANIELA DUCA	Oct 2020 - Dec 2020

- Contributing to a Text cleaning WebApp called Texti
- Working on NLP transformations in Python and documentation
- Results from the Fellowship are described here.

Computational Social Science Department, GESIS

Cologne, Germany Oct 2018 - Present

Doctoral Researcher. Advisors: Prof. Claudia Wagner, Dr, Katrin Weller

- · Identifying, Characterizing and Quantifying errors that occur when measuring attitudes from Digital Traces
- Building robust and interpretable NLP methods for measuring social science phenomena

How Does Counterfactually Augmented Data Impact Models for Social Computing

• Large scale Twitter data collection using Amazon Web Services (AWS) as a service for Social Scientists.

Precog Research Lab, IIIT Delhi

New Delhi, India

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE. ADVISORS: PROF. PONNURANGAM KUMARAGURU AND PROF. ARUN BALAJI BUDURU

Dec 2017 - Aug 2018

- · Landscaping the fake like marketplace on Instagram and characterizing fake likers, and their attack vectors.
- Detecting Multimodal Hatespeech on Social Media

CHILI Lab, École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne

Lausanne, Switzerland

SUMMER INTERN, ADVISOR: PROF. PIERRE DILLENBOURG

Jun 2017- Aug 2017

· Worked on inferring dependencies between EPFL courses based on Concept Mining and grading patterns

Nanyang Technological University

Singapore

RESEARCH ASSISTANT, ADVISOR: PROF. ANWITAMAN DUTTA

Jan 2017– May 2017

• Master's Thesis: Worked on detecting fake engagement on Instagram.

Presentations and Talks

A Total Error Framework for Digital Traces of Humans

Virtual

DGS KONGRESS

Sep 2020

(Mis)Measuring Attitudes from Digital Traces

Virtual

THIRD ANNUAL POLITICS AND COMPUTATIONAL SOCIAL SCIENCES CONFERENCE (PACSS)

Aug 2020

Measuring Opinions towards Politicians in Tweets

Virtual

NEWS AND PUBLIC OPINION (NECO)

June 2020

Teaching, Mentorship, and Academic Service

Translation Tutorial on the Total Error Paradigm for Social Inferences

Barcelona, Spain

FAT* 2020

Jan 2020

• Tutorial on diagnosing errors and biases in observational studies from digital traces

Introduction to Python and Data Science with Python

Cologne, Germany

New Delhi, India

University of Cologne

Oct. 2019

· Interactive, hands-on five-day lecture series for teaching introductory python concepts to social science doctoral candidates

Mentorship

IIIT DELHI

- · Vani Agarwal. Master's Thesis. Improving Content Moderation through Co-Training
- Kushagra Singh. Bachelor's Thesis. Information Extraction Tools for Code-Mixed Hindi-English Social Media Content

Reviewer

CSCW (2019, 2020), THEWEBCONF (2020, 2021), ICWSM (2019, 2020, 2021, 2022), EMNLP (2020)

Skills

Programming: Python, R, Java, C++, C, MongoDB, SQL, Bash, Javascript,

Libraries/Tools: scikit-learn, pytorch, tensorflow, keras, pandas, NLTK, NetworkX, AWS, Amazon Mechanical Turk

OCTOBER 28, 2021

INDIRA SEN · CV